<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title type="text">what if?</title>
    <id>https://what-if.xkcd.com/feed.atom</id>
    <updated>2022-11-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="https://what-if.xkcd.com/feed.atom" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://what-if.xkcd.com" rel="alternate" title="What If?" type="text/html"/>
    <author>
        <name>xkcd</name>
        <email>whatif@xkcd.com</email>
    </author>
    <icon>https://what-if.xkcd.com/favicon.ico</icon>
    <logo>https://what-if.xkcd.com/favicon.ico</logo>
    <subtitle type="text">Answering your hypothetical questions with physics, every Tuesday.</subtitle>
    <entry>
        <id>urn:uuid:faee02a9-f6ea-51dc-99ad-a21c38c2e5e2</id>
        <title type="text">Star Ownership</title>
        <updated>2022-11-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>xkcd</name>
            <email>whatif@xkcd.com</email>
        </author>
        <content type="html">
            &lt;p id=&#34;question&#34;&gt;If every country&amp;#39;s airspace extended up forever, 
            which country would own the largest percentage of the galaxy at any given time?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p id=&#34;attribute&#34;&gt;Reuven Lazarus&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today&amp;#39;s question is adapted from &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/what-if-2/&#34;
            &gt;What If 2: Additional Serious Scientific Answers to Absurd Hypothetical Questions&lt;/a&gt;
            , which contains many more What If answers and is &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/what-if-2/&#34;&gt;available now&lt;
            /a&gt;!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to Australia, new rulers of the galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The Australian flag has a number of symbols on it, including five stars that represent the stars of the Southern Cross.
            &lt;span&gt;[1]&lt;/span&gt; Based on the answer to this question, maybe their flag designers should think bigger.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Hopefully it goes better than the 2015-2016 New Zealand flag redesign referendum.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/161/star-ownership_1.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Countries in the southern hemisphere have an advantage when it comes to star ownership. Earth&amp;#39;s axis is tilted relative to the Milky Way; our North Pole points generally away from the galaxy&amp;#39;s center.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;If you&amp;#39;re going to fire off some sci-fi weapon at an enemy and you don&amp;#39;t want to hit any inhabited planets if you miss, try to maneuver so the enemy is north of you.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/161/star-ownership_2.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;If each country&amp;#39;s airspace extended upward forever, the core of the galaxy would stay under the control of countries in the southern hemisphere, changing hands over the course of each day as the Earth rotates.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;At its peak, Australia would control more stars than any other country. The supermassive black hole at the core of the galaxy would enter Australian airspace every day south of Brisbane, near the small town of Broadwater.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Population about 4,000 people and one supermassive black hole&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/161/star-ownership_3.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;After about an hour, almost the entire galactic core—along with a substantial chunk of the disk—would be within Australian jurisdiction.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;I don&amp;#39;t understand this election results map.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/161/star-ownership_4.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;At various times throughout the day, the galactic core would pass through the domain of South Africa, Lesotho, Brazil, Argentina, and Chile. The United States, Europe, and most of Asia would have to be content with outer sections of the galactic disk.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The northern hemisphere isn&amp;#39;t left with the dregs, though. The outer galactic disk has some cool things in it—like Cygnus X-1, a black hole currently devouring a supergiant star.&lt;span&gt;[2]&lt;/span&gt; Each day, as the core of the galaxy crossed the Pacific, Cygnus X-1 would enter the United States&amp;#39;s airspace over North Carolina.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Maybe the Wright brothers picked Kitty Hawk because they thought the black hole would tug their aircraft upward a little.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/161/star-ownership_5.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;While owning a black hole would be cool, the United States would also have millions of planetary systems constantly moving in and out of its territory—which might cause some problems.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The star 47 Ursae Majoris has at least three planets and probably more. If any of those planets have life on them, then once a day all that life passes through the United States. That means that there&amp;#39;s a period of a few minutes each day where any murders on those planets technically happen in New Jersey.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Luckily for the New Jersey court system, altitudes above about 12 miles are generally considered &amp;quot;high seas.&amp;quot; According to the American Bar Association&amp;#39;s Winter 2012 issue of the Admiralty and Maritime Law Committee Newsletter, this means that deaths above these altitudes—even deaths in space—are arguably covered by the 1920 Death on the High Seas Act, or DOHSA.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;But if any aliens on 47 Ursae Majoris are considering bringing a lawsuit in a US court under DOHSA, they&amp;#39;re going to be disappointed. DOHSA has a statute of limitations of 3 years, but 47 Ursae Majoris is more than 40 light-years away...&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Einstein was in on the murder!&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/161/star-ownership_6.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;...which means it&amp;#39;s physically impossible for them to file charges in time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] Epsilon Crucis has five points, while the others have seven, implying that the view of Epsilon is from a telescope with different lens geometry from the others. Minor symbolic/graphic design choice? Or clue to a secret multiversal alliance between parallel universe Australias? No way to know for sure!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[2] Cygnus X-1 was the subject of a famous bet between astrophysicists Stephen Hawking and Kip Thorne over whether it was a black hole or not. Hawking, who had spent much of his career studying black holes, bet that it wasn&amp;#39;t. He figured that if black holes turned out not to exist, at least he would win the bet as a consolation prize. In the end, luckily for his legacy, he lost.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://what-if.xkcd.com/161/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><published>2022-11-01T00:00:00Z</published></entry><entry><id>urn:uuid:c1d44ca7-4df2-54c7-94cf-5c5efbc9d00b</id><title type="text">Transatlantic Car Rental</title><updated>2022-09-06T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name>xkcd</name><email>whatif@xkcd.com</email></author><content type="html">&lt;p id=&#34;question&#34;&gt;My daughter recently received her driver&amp;#39;s permit in the US, and aspires to visit mainland Europe someday. She has learned enough about the rules of the road to know never to drive into the ocean; however, she jokingly suggested that given a sufficient quantity of rental cars, she could eventually get to Europe by driving east repeatedly. The question is, how many vehicles would it take to build a car-bridge across the Atlantic?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p id=&#34;attribute&#34;&gt;Eric Munson&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;After extensive research, I can conclusively state that this would be a violation of your rental car agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Also, you would disrupt ocean circulation in the North Atlantic, potentially seriously altering the climate in the northern hemisphere. That&amp;#39;s very bad, although not necessarily a violation of your rental car agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;The friend thing might also depend on the friend.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/160/rental.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;If you try to drive from the US to Europe, your car will stop working pretty quickly, since according to Google Maps there&amp;#39;s a large hole between them and it&amp;#39;s full of water. Once your car gets stuck, you&amp;#39;ll have to leave it there and go get another one.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;The North Atlantic Treaty Organization has existed for decades, yet has made no progress on defeating the North Atlantic.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/160/hole.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Driving your second car onto the roof of the sunken first one could get you a little closer to Europe. If we assume you&amp;#39;re starting in Boston and heading toward Lisbon, using a car as a bridge would get you about a millionth of the way there, since Boston and Lisbon are about a million car-lengths apart. If the Atlantic Ocean were two feet deep, you could make a bridge out of a million cars placed end to end. Unfortunately, a quick rewatch of &lt;em&gt;Titanic&lt;/em&gt; (1997) suggests that the Atlantic Ocean is more than two feet deep. You&amp;#39;ll quickly have to start piling up cars in multiple layers.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Diagram from the advanced section of the driver&amp;#39;s manual&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/160/layers.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;At first, when the bridge would be just one or two cars high, you could stack them in a single vertical column. But as the water gets deeper, you&amp;#39;ll need to create a wider base to keep the wall of cars from tipping over.&lt;span&gt;[1]&lt;/span&gt; The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Atlantic_Current&#34;&gt;North Atlantic current&lt;/a&gt; would push against the car causeway, but the tipping force from the water motion would be relatively minor compared to the pile&amp;#39;s tendency to topple under its own weight.&lt;span&gt;[2]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Diagram from the forbidden section of the driver&amp;#39;s manual.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/160/triangular.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;As you built your bridge out into the deep ocean, the cars on the bottom of the stack would be crushed. The pressure crushing them wouldn&amp;#39;t be the water pressure. Once the windows broke and the interior of the car flooded, the pressure would equalize and the cars would hold their shape, relatively unaffected by the weight of the ocean above them. Instead, what would crush the cars would be the weight of the other cars sitting on top of them.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Even when they&amp;#39;re underwater, cars weigh a lot. About 50% of the weight of modern cars is steel and iron, which is much denser than water,&lt;span&gt;[3]&lt;/span&gt; so submerged cars are still quite heavy—about 60% to 70% of their surface weight, depending on their exact composition. The cars on the bottom of a mile-high stack would be subjected to extreme pressures, even greater than what they experience in hydraulic car crushers. Those crushers&lt;span&gt;[4]&lt;/span&gt; are capable of flattening a car into a pancake a foot or two thick, and the same thing would happen to the cars on the bottom of our stack.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Parallel parking&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/160/flat.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The first part of your bridge to Europe would be over the continental shelf, where the water is relatively shallow—just a few hundred crushed cars deep.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Your bridge will briefly cross onto land in Nova Scotia, which should be fun.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/160/atlanticmap.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;You&amp;#39;d still need a lot of cars to form this shallow-water portion of the bridge; getting out to the edge of the continental shelf would take about a billion of them, which is probably close to the total number of cars in the world. Parking lots hold about 1 car per 30 square meters, so a billion cars would cover a large portion of eastern Massachusetts.&lt;span&gt;[5]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;After the continental shelf, the water gets a lot deeper. The deep-ocean portion of your bridge would require a lot more cars—likely about a trillion of them. This is far more cars than exist in the world; a parking lot big enough to hold them would take up most of the Earth&amp;#39;s land area.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;So you can&amp;#39;t rent anywhere close to a billion &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; a trillion cars—Enterprise, for example, only has about &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.enterprise.com/en/about.html&#34;&gt;half a million&lt;/a&gt; cars in its fleet. But if you tried, you&amp;#39;d run into other problems, too. I got a copy of a recent Enterprise rental car agreement, and I have some bad news:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;4. Prohibited Use and Termination of Right to Use.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;a. Renter agrees to the following limits on use:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[...]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(4) &lt;b&gt;Vehicle shall not be used&lt;/b&gt; for: any illegal purposes; &lt;b&gt;in any illegal or reckless manner&lt;/b&gt;; in a race or speed contest; or to tow or push anything.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[...]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(8) Vehicle shall not be loaded in excess of Vehicle’s Gross Vehicle Weight Rating [...]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(9) &lt;b&gt;Vehicle shall not be driven on an unpaved road or off-road.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;You&amp;#39;d clearly be in violation of 4(a)(9) by driving it off-road. I think you&amp;#39;d also be violating 4(a)(4) and probably 4(a)(8) as well. This would result in you being—at minimum—on the hook for the total cost of the rental car.&lt;span&gt;[6]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Some credit cards offer coverage for rental car damage, so you might think that—if you&amp;#39;re a high-status cardholder—you could try to get the company to foot the bill. Unfortunately, I took a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.americanexpress.com/content/dam/amex/us/credit-cards/features-benefits/policies/NAC-Benefit-Guides/CRLDI_Benefit_Guide_371.397_EDT_02.20REV_10.20.pdf&#34;&gt;the agreement&lt;/a&gt; for the American Express Centurion card, and the &amp;quot;What is &lt;em&gt;Not&lt;/em&gt; covered&amp;quot; section clearly addresses this scenario:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;b&gt;What is &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline&#34;&gt;Not&lt;/span&gt; Covered?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;ANY COVERED EVENT BASED UPON OR ARISING OUT OF: &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;[...]&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3. Use of the Rental Vehicle in &lt;strong&gt;violation of the terms and conditions of the Rental Agreement&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[...] &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;8. &lt;b&gt;off-road operation&lt;/b&gt; [...] of the Rental Vehicle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[...] &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;11. &lt;b&gt;intentional damage&lt;/b&gt; [...] to the Rental Vehicle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Interestingly, American Express will also not cover damages incurred by using the rental car in a war:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;[...] 1. War or acts of war (whether declared or undeclared), service in the armed forces or units auxiliary to it [...]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;This rule could actually end up being relevant here. Your car bridge across the Atlantic, in addition to potentially &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlantic_meridional_overturning_circulation&#34;&gt;disrupting ocean circulation&lt;/a&gt;, would &lt;a href=&#34;https://digital-commons.usnwc.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1429&amp;amp;context=ils&#34;&gt;cut off shipping access&lt;/a&gt; to northern Europe and much of Atlantic Canada...&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;...which may qualify as a naval blockade.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;How many points is this on my license?&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/160/blockade.png&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] A glance at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/search?q=junk+car+piles&amp;amp;tbm=isch&#34;&gt;piles of cars&lt;/a&gt; in a junkyard suggests that they often end up in stacks with an angle of repose of 30 or 45 degrees, but a stack with a 10°-15° angle of repose at the bottom should be stable once the cars are sufficiently crushed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[2] Mike Ashby&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://cushman.host.dartmouth.edu/courses/engs171/UsefulSolutionsForStandardProblems.pdf&#34;&gt;Useful Solutions to Standard Problems&lt;/a&gt; is a fantastic resource for these kinds of calculations. In this case, you could use it to figure out how a column of cars will topple, which would require an estimate of the compressibility of a stack of cars at different stages of flattening. I used specs from hydraulic car crushers to come up with my rough estimates here, but these estimates could probably be refined with experiment if you know &lt;a href=&#34;https://cars.usnews.com/cars-trucks/features/jay-lenos-car-collection&#34;&gt;someone with a lot of cars&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[3] Citation: You don&amp;#39;t see a lot of anchors floating around.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[4] Most famous, of course, for imperiling George Frankly in an episode of MathNet, the detective show on PBS&amp;#39;s Square One TV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[5] Apparently all the world&amp;#39;s cars would take up slightly more space than all the world&amp;#39;s people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[6] If you continue to operate the vehicle in such a manner, 4(d) says the company has the right to notify police that it has been stolen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://what-if.xkcd.com/160/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><published>2022-09-06T00:00:00Z</published></entry><entry><id>urn:uuid:de993890-836d-56ef-bdae-e343f576aa1a</id><title type="text">Hailstones</title><updated>2022-07-06T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name>xkcd</name><email>whatif@xkcd.com</email></author><content type="html">&lt;p id=&#34;question&#34;&gt;My 4 year old son and I were wondering about soccer ball sized hail today. How much damage would a hail storm with size 5 soccer ball sized hail do?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p id=&#34;attribute&#34;&gt;Michael Grill&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;When you think about it, it&amp;#39;s honestly kind of weird that hailstones haven&amp;#39;t killed all of us already. I mean, they&amp;#39;re chunks of ice that plunge from the sky!&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;RIP&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/159/deaths.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Hailstones fall from really high up. There&amp;#39;s a popular myth that a penny dropped from the Empire State Building can kill you. The myth isn&amp;#39;t true,&lt;span&gt;[1]&lt;/span&gt; but for anyone who believes it, hailstones should be terrifying—after all, they often fall from the height of &lt;em&gt;ten&lt;/em&gt; Empire State Buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;I know modern skyscrapers are extremely safe, but I would be pretty nervous going up that one.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/159/tenempire.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Luckily, the same thing that saves us from falling pennies also generally protects us from hailstones: Air resistance. As they fall, both pennies and hailstones quickly reach terminal velocity, the speed at which drag balances out gravity and prevents them from speeding up any more. For a small hailstone the size of a pea or a marble, terminal velocity might be only 10 or 20 miles per hour, the speed of an object tossed across a room. Getting hit by them isn&amp;#39;t comfortable, but it&amp;#39;s not likely to cause serious injury.&lt;span&gt;[2]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;ISO standard impact speed calibration method, developed by an ISO employee who everyone else at the office hates&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/159/bonk.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Large hailstones travel much faster than small ones and can be a lot more dangerous. The terminal velocity of a golf-ball-sized hailstone is about 60 miles per hour,&lt;span&gt;[3]&lt;/span&gt; which could easily cause serious injury. Large hailstorms often cause &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/search?tbm=isch&amp;amp;q=hail+car+windows&#34;&gt;extreme damage to cars&lt;/a&gt;, and the largest hailstones can be deadly. A &lt;a href=&#34;http://edition.cnn.com/2002/WEATHER/07/22/weather.china.hail/&#34;&gt;storm in China in 2002&lt;/a&gt; dropped egg-sized and baseball-sized hailstones that killed several dozen people and hospitalized many others.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Luckily, deaths from hail aren&amp;#39;t very common, for two main reasons: First, because hailstones big enough to be deadly are rare, and second, because when there&amp;#39;s a thunderstorm severe enough to produce such large hail, people generally try to take shelter.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;They say most car accidents happen within 10 miles of the home, so I maintain an official residence and carefully avoid a 10-mile circle around it while driving&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/159/relativerisk.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;A hailstone the size and shape of a regulation soccer ball would be more than twice the weight of the heaviest hailstones on record. It would have a terminal velocity of roughly 140 miles per hour, which is really fast. If one of them hit your car, it wouldn&amp;#39;t just dent the body or crack the windshield, it could punch right through the roof. Sheltering indoors might not be enough to protect you, unless you had a particularly sturdy roof or possibly several floors above you.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Do not attempt. Professional drivers on a closed course who were not warned ahead of time about what we were doing.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/159/car.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;When a hailstorm is nearby, it&amp;#39;s good to take shelter even if you&amp;#39;re not right below the storm. As a hailstone forms in a thunderstorm updraft, it bounces around like popcorn in a popcorn machine. Usually, it falls out of the bottom of the storm, but sometimes it&amp;#39;s ejected out of the top or sides, then carried by wind to fall some distance from the storm. Aircraft flying near thunderstorms have been hit by hail when they have nothing but blue sky above them.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;pop pop pop pop&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/159/popcorn.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Real hailstones, especially large ones, aren&amp;#39;t round like a soccer ball. As they tumble around in a thunderstorm, they grow via water freezing onto their sides. If they have a lump on one side, the protrusion can collect more water and grow faster than the areas around it, forming a blobby appendage. Liquid water can also run out to the edges of a rotating hailstone and freeze, forming icicle-like features.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Hailstones are bouba&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/159/lobes.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The weird shapes of large hailstones are good news for us ground-dwellers with breakable bones, because these protrusions tend to increase their drag and lower their terminal velocity.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;But the weird shapes of hailstones also raises an interesting possibility. If a hailstone had just the right combination of lobes, it&amp;#39;s possible—if unlikely—that it might happen to form a lifting body. This strange category of aircraft—which includes the Space Shuttle, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NASA_M2-F1&#34;&gt;M2-F1&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dream_Chaser&#34;&gt;Dream Chaser&lt;/a&gt;—can be unexpectedly aerodynamic despite their compact shapes, capable of gliding or even swoops.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Project Hailstone definitely sounds like a weird military space thing, but AFAIK it isn&amp;#39;t the name of any actual project.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/159/glideratio.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s unlikely that any gliding hail has ever been observed, but in the 4 billion years that Earth has had water and thunderstorms, there have probably been some pretty strange hailstones. Not only has there likely been one the &lt;em&gt;size&lt;/em&gt; of a soccer ball ...&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Goooooooooal&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/159/soccer.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;... there might even have been one able to score a goal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] Mythbusters tried it in Season 1 Episode 7 and found that the penny would really sting and make you go &amp;quot;ow!!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[2] While dropping a penny on someone from the height of the Empire State Building wouldn&amp;#39;t kill them, dropping the Empire State Building on a them from the height of a penny &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt;, as demonstrated by the tragic demise of Jebediah Mythbuster in the pilot episode of the show eventually named in his memory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[3] A little slower than an actual golf ball, thanks to the golf ball&amp;#39;s greater weight and those weird drag-reducing dimples.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://what-if.xkcd.com/159/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><published>2022-07-06T00:00:00Z</published></entry><entry><id>urn:uuid:dafca21e-a008-5bb1-975d-bfaadfd2a13d</id><title type="text">Hot Banana</title><updated>2022-05-04T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name>xkcd</name><email>whatif@xkcd.com</email></author><content type="html">&lt;p id=&#34;question&#34;&gt;I heard that bananas are radioactive. If they are radioactive, then they radiate energy. How many bananas would you need to power a house?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p id=&#34;attribute&#34;&gt;Kang JI&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Bananas are radioactive. But don&amp;#39;t worry, it&amp;#39;s fine.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;SLIPPERY WHEN DRY&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/158/hazard.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Bananas are radioactive because they contain potassium, some of which is the radioactive isotope potassium-40. The factoid about banana radioactivity was popularized by nuclear engineers trying to reassure people&lt;span&gt;[1]&lt;/span&gt; that small doses of radiation are normal and not necessarily dangerous. Of course, this kind of thing can backfire.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;In banana terms, a chest x-ray has a rich, sweet flavor and is high in starchy carbohydrates.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/158/nomore.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Thanks to their use as a radiation dose comparison, bananas now have a reputation as an especially radioactive food, but they&amp;#39;re really not. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/crchandbookofrad0001unse/page/620/mode/2up&#34;&gt;CRC Handbook of Radiation Measurement and Protection&lt;/a&gt;, the source of the original data behind the banana factoid, lists lots of other foods with more potassium-40 than bananas, including coconuts, peanuts, and sweet potatoes. A large cheese pizza might be three times more radioactive than a banana,&lt;span&gt;[2]&lt;/span&gt; and your own body emits a lot more radiation than either.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Large pizza, extra sieverts&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/158/pizza.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Potassium-40 decays slowly, with individual atoms sitting around for millions or billions of years before quantum randomness finally triggers their decay. Imagine you&amp;#39;re an atom of potassium; every second you roll 21 dice. If they all come up 6s, you decay.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Now I want to go play Dice Wars again&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/158/dice.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;There are gazillions&lt;span&gt;[3]&lt;/span&gt; of atoms of potassium-40 in a banana. In any given second, 10 or 15 of them make that all-sixes roll, spit out a high-energy particle, and become stable calcium or argon.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Troubling new LHC results confirm that radioactive nuclei make a tiny grunting noise before expelling a particle&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/158/myturn.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;That high-energy particle released by the expiring potassium atom&lt;span&gt;[4]&lt;/span&gt; will promptly bonk&lt;span&gt;[5]&lt;/span&gt; into other atoms, leaving everything vibrating with extra heat energy. In theory, you could use this heat energy to do work—that&amp;#39;s how the Mars rovers Curiosity and Opportunity are powered.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The Mars rovers use plutonium, which decays millions of times per second, releasing a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of power. By comparison, the 15 decays per second from one banana work out to a couple of picowatts of power, roughly the power consumption of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orders_of_magnitude_(power)#Below_1_W&#34;&gt;a single human cell&lt;/a&gt;. Even if you captured that decay energy with perfect efficiency, powering a house would require about 300 quadrillion&lt;span&gt;[6]&lt;/span&gt; bananas, which would form a heap large enough to bury most of the skyscrapers in the NYC metro area.&lt;span&gt;[7]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Why I&amp;#39;m Leaving New York&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/158/nycpile.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The potassium-40 in bananas is a terrible source of energy. But that&amp;#39;s okay, because you know what&amp;#39;s a great energy source? The banana itself! A banana contains about 100 calories of food energy, and if you &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/10/12/2119&#34;&gt;incinerate whole bananas as fuel&lt;/a&gt;, it would only take about 10 bunches per day to keep your house running.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Burning bananas directly for heat can be less efficient than using them to run a heat pump.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/158/10bunches.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for New York City, which we buried in bananas a moment ago while trying to make the radiation idea work (sorry!), radioactivity vs chemical energy isn&amp;#39;t an either/or thing. If you piled up a lot of bananas, they would start to release that chemical energy, one way or another. The sun-baked banana pile would start to rot. The heat from the bananas decomposing in the atmosphere would immediately swamp the heat from radioactivity. The sun-dried bananas would dry, crack, and eventually burn.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;The Curious George Memorial Banana Fire&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/158/nycbananafire.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Decomposition by anaerobic bacteria deep in the pile would produce various gases, including highly flammable methane. As they bubbled up to the surface of the burning banana swamp, they could ignite; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.organics-recycling.org.uk/page.php?article=2142&#34;&gt;gas buildup from food waste&lt;/a&gt; is a major industrial explosion hazard.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;The fabled Gros Michel banana had far more raw explosive power, but after the nuclear test ban treaty was replaced by the Cavendish&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/158/nycbananaexplosion.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;So don&amp;#39;t worry about the radioactivity in bananas. It&amp;#39;s the &lt;em&gt;rest&lt;/em&gt; of the banana that&amp;#39;s the real threat. But if you&amp;#39;re willing to risk the danger, you could power a lot more than just your house. With just a modest weekly supply of bananas—enough to cover Liberty Island in NYC...&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;A modest pile of bananas&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/158/islandpile.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;...you could power the entire city.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Give us your peels, your cores, your piled biomasses...&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/158/liberty.png&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] After nuclear engineering, this is the main pastime of nuclear engineers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[2] Google has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/search?q=pizza+potassium&#34;&gt;handy tool&lt;/a&gt; for looking up the amount of potassium in foods, which even lets you select specific pizza brands. But for some reason, if you select Pizza Hut Pepperoni Pizza, your only serving size options are either &amp;quot;1 slice&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;40 pizzas.&amp;quot; Nothing in between.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[3] There are about 800,000,000,000,000,000 of them, which is probably quadrillions or quintillions or something, but life is too short to sit around counting zeros and then looking up the Latin prefixes for big numbers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[4] RIP&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[5] The technical term is THUNK.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[6] Fine, I looked it up this time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[7] It&amp;#39;s 300 quadrillion bananas, Michael—what can it cost, 3 quintillion dollars?&lt;/p&gt;</content><link href="https://what-if.xkcd.com/158/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><published>2022-05-04T00:00:00Z</published></entry><entry><id>https://what-if.xkcd.com/157/</id><title type="text">Earth-Moon Fire Pole</title><updated>2018-05-21T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name>xkcd</name><email>whatif@xkcd.com</email></author><content type="html">&lt;p id=&#34;question&#34;&gt;My son (5y) asked me today: If there were a kind of a fireman&amp;#39;s pole from the Moon down to the Earth, how long would it take to slide all the way from the Moon to the Earth?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p id=&#34;attribute&#34;&gt;Ramon Schönborn, Germany&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;First, let&amp;#39;s get a few things out of the way:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;In real life, we can&amp;#39;t put a metal pole between the Earth and the Moon.&lt;span&gt;[1]&lt;/span&gt; The end of the pole near the Moon would be pulled toward the Moon by the Moon&amp;#39;s gravity, and the rest of it would be pulled back down to the Earth by the Earth&amp;#39;s gravity. The pole would be torn in half.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Diagram from NASA Apollo planning archives&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/grav.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Another problem with this plan. The Earth&amp;#39;s surface spins faster than the Moon goes around, so the end that dangled down to the Earth would break off if you tried to connect it to the ground:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Professional driver on closed course. Do not attempt.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/break.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s one more problem:&lt;span&gt;[2]&lt;/span&gt; The Moon doesn&amp;#39;t always stay the same distance from Earth. Its orbit takes it closer and farther away. It&amp;#39;s not a big difference,&lt;span&gt;[3]&lt;/span&gt; but it&amp;#39;s enough that the bottom 50,000 km of your fire station pole would be squished against the Earth once a month.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;But let&amp;#39;s ignore those problems! What if we had a magical pole that dangled from the Moon down to just above the Earth&amp;#39;s surface, expanding and contracting so it never quite touched the ground? How long would it take to slide down from the Moon?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;If you stood next to the end of the pole on the Moon, a problem would become clear right away: You have to slide &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; the pole, and that&amp;#39;s not how sliding works.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;NEXT REST AREA: L1 (36,000 miles) (NO FACILITIES)&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/slide.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Instead of sliding, you&amp;#39;ll have to climb.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;People can climb poles pretty fast. World-record pole climbers&lt;span&gt;[4]&lt;/span&gt; can climb at over a meter per second in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=pole+speed+climbing&#34;&gt;championship competition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;span&gt;[5]&lt;/span&gt; On the Moon, gravity is much weaker, so it will probably be easier to climb. On the other hand, you&amp;#39;ll have to wear a spacesuit, so that will probably slow you down a little.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;If you climb up the pole far enough, Earth&amp;#39;s gravity will take over and start pulling you down. When you&amp;#39;re hanging onto the pole, there are three forces pulling on you: The Earth&amp;#39;s gravity pulling you toward Earth, the Moon&amp;#39;s gravity pulling you away from Earth, and centrifugal force&lt;span&gt;[6]&lt;/span&gt; from the swinging pole pulling you away from Earth.&lt;span&gt;[7]&lt;/span&gt; At first, the combination of the Moon&amp;#39;s gravity and centrifugal force are stronger, pulling you toward the Moon, but as you get closer to the Earth, Earth&amp;#39;s gravity takes over. The Earth is pretty big, so you reach this point—which is known as the L1 Lagrange point—while you&amp;#39;re still pretty close to the Moon.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;In countries with right-hand drive spacecraft, these points are referred to as R1 through R5.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/l1.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for you, space is big, so &amp;quot;pretty close&amp;quot; is still a long way. Even if you climb at better-than-world-record speed, it will still take you several years to get to the L1 crossover point.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;As you approach the L1 point, you&amp;#39;ll start to be able to switch from climbing to pushing-and-gliding: You can push once and then coast a long distance up the pole. You don&amp;#39;t have to wait to stop, either—you can grab the pole again and give yourself a push to move even faster, like a skateboarder kicking several times to speed up.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;SOURCE: I&amp;#39;m pretty sure this is a dream I&amp;#39;ve had.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/climb.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Eventually, as you reach the vicinity of the L1 point and are no longer fighting gravity, the only limit on your speed will be how quickly you can grab the pole and &amp;quot;throw&amp;quot; it past you. The best baseball pitchers can move their hands at about 100 mph while flinging objects past them, so you probably can&amp;#39;t expect to move much faster than that.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: While you&amp;#39;re flinging yourself along, be careful not to drift out of reach of the pole. Hopefully you brought some kind of safety line so you can recover if that happens.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;This is definitely a dream I&amp;#39;ve had.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/oops.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;After another few weeks of gliding along the pole, you&amp;#39;ll start to feel gravity take over, speeding you up faster than you can go by pushing yourself. When this happens, be careful—soon, you&amp;#39;ll need to start worrying about going &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; fast.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;As you approach the Earth and the pull of its gravity increases, you&amp;#39;ll start to speed up quite a bit. If you don&amp;#39;t stop yourself, you&amp;#39;ll reach the top of the atmosphere at roughly escape velocity—11 km/s&lt;span&gt;[8]&lt;/span&gt;—and the impact with the air will produce so much heat that you risk burning up. Spacecraft deal with this problem by including heat shields, which are capable of absorbing and dissipating this heat without burning up the spacecraft behind it.&lt;span&gt;[9]&lt;/span&gt; Since you have this handy metal pole, you can control your descent by clamping onto it and controlling your rate of descent through friction.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;There may not be any sound in space, but you&amp;#39;ll feel it conducted through your bones.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/clamp.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Make sure to keep your speed low during the whole approach and descent—and, if necessary, pausing to let your hands or brakepads cool down—rather than waiting until the end to try to slow down. If you get up to escape velocity, then at the last minute remember that you need to slow down, you&amp;#39;ll be in for an unpleasant surprise as you try to grab on to the pole. At best, you&amp;#39;ll be flung away and plummet to your death. At worst, your hands and the surface of the pole will both be converted into exciting new forms of matter, and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; you&amp;#39;ll be flung away and plummet to your death.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;It&amp;#39;s fine, I brought some oven mitts.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/grab.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Assuming you descend slowly and enter the atmosphere in a controlled manner, you&amp;#39;ll soon encounter your next problem: Your pole isn&amp;#39;t moving at the same speed as the Earth. Not even close. The land and atmosphere below you are moving very fast relative to you. You&amp;#39;re about to drop into some extremely strong winds.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Don&amp;#39;t worry about it.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/nervous.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The Moon orbits around the Earth at a speed of roughly one kilometer per second, making a wide circle&lt;span&gt;[10]&lt;/span&gt; every 29 days or so. That&amp;#39;s how fast the top end of our hypothetical fire pole will be traveling. The bottom end of the pole makes a much smaller circle in the same amount of time, moving at an average speed of only about 35 mph relative to the center of the Moon&amp;#39;s orbit:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;35 mph doesn&amp;#39;t sound too bad.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/bigcircle.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;35 miles per hour doesn&amp;#39;t sound bad. Unfortunately for you, the Earth is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; spinning,&lt;span&gt;[11]&lt;/span&gt; and its surface moves a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; faster than 35 mph; at the Equator, it can reach over 1,000 miles per hour.&lt;span&gt;[12]&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8203;&lt;span&gt;[13]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;1000 mph does sound bad.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/bigcircle2.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Even though the end of the pole is moving slowly relative to the Earth as a whole, it&amp;#39;s moving very fast relative to the &lt;em&gt;surface&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;Is it just me, or is the atmosphere piling up in front of the pole? Is it too late to turn around?&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/bigcircle3.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Asking how fast the pole is moving relative to the surface is effectively the same as asking what the &amp;quot;ground speed&amp;quot; of the Moon is. This is tricky to calculate, because the Moon&amp;#39;s ground speed varies over time in a complicated way. Luckily for us, it doesn&amp;#39;t vary &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; much—it&amp;#39;s usually somewhere between 390 and 450 m/s, or a little over Mach 1—so figuring out the precise value isn&amp;#39;t necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;I don&amp;#39;t see what you&amp;#39;re so worried about.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/stalling.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s buy a little time by trying to figure it out anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The Moon&amp;#39;s ground speed varies pretty regularly, making a kind of sine wave. It peaks twice every month as it passes over the fast-moving equator, then reaches a minimum when it&amp;#39;s over the slower-moving tropics. Its orbital speed also changes depending on whether it&amp;#39;s at the close or far point in its orbit. This leads to a roughly sine-wave shaped ground speed:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;DO NOT USE THIS GRAPH FOR PLANNING PURPOSES. It&amp;#39;s not that it isn&amp;#39;t accurate, it&amp;#39;s just that any kind of plan that involves this type of data is probably a bad one.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/fastslow.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Well, ready to jump?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;There&amp;#39;s always something else to calculate.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/calculate.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Ok, fine. There&amp;#39;s one other cycle we can take into account to &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; nail down the Moon&amp;#39;s ground speed. The Moon&amp;#39;s orbit is tilted by about 5° relative to the Earth-Sun plane, while the Earth&amp;#39;s axis is tilted by 23.5°. This means that the Moon&amp;#39;s latitude changes the way the Sun&amp;#39;s does, moving from the northern tropics to the southern tropics twice a year.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;However, the Moon&amp;#39;s orbit is also tilted, and this tilt rotates on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metonic_cycle&#34;&gt;an 18.9-year cycle&lt;/a&gt;. When the Moon&amp;#39;s tilt is in the same direction as the Earth&amp;#39;s, it stays 5° closer to the Equator than the Sun, and when it&amp;#39;s in the opposite direction, it reaches more extreme latitudes. When the Moon is over a point farther from the equator, it has a lower &amp;quot;ground speed,&amp;quot; so the lower end of the sine wave goes lower. Here&amp;#39;s the plot of the Moon&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;ground speed&amp;quot; over the next few decades:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;\&amp;quot;The 2020s will have the lowest average Moon speed of any decade in my lifetime\&amp;quot; is a new contender for the least consequential thing I&amp;#39;ve ever learned.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/hazysin.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The Moon&amp;#39;s top speed stays pretty constant, but the lowest speed rises and falls with an 18.9-year cycle. The lowest speed of the next cycle will be on May 1st, 2025, so if you want to wait until 2025 to slide down, you can hit the atmosphere when the pole is moving at only 390 m/s relative to the Earth&amp;#39;s surface.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;If you&amp;#39;re reading this before May 1st, 2025, please pause your reading until that date, then resume at the next paragraph.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/wait.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;When you do finally enter the atmosphere, you&amp;#39;ll be coming down near the edge of the tropics. Try to avoid the &lt;a href=&#34;https://earth.nullschool.net/#current/wind/isobaric/250hPa/orthographic=326.35,-1.08,372&#34;&gt;tropical jet stream&lt;/a&gt;, an upper-level air current which blows in the same direction the Earth rotates. If your pole happens to go through it, it could add another 50-100 m/s to the wind speed.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Regardless of where you come down, you&amp;#39;ll need to contend with supersonic winds, so you should wear lots of protective gear.&lt;span&gt;[15]&lt;/span&gt; Make sure you&amp;#39;re tightly attached to the pole, since the wind and various shockwaves will be violently battering and jolting you around. People often say, &amp;quot;It&amp;#39;s not the fall that kills you, it&amp;#39;s the sudden stop at the end.&amp;quot; Unfortunately, in this case, it&amp;#39;s probably going to be both.&lt;span&gt;[17]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;SOURCE: Data from a NASA experiment/fun prank&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/shockwaves.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;At some point, to reach the ground, you&amp;#39;re going to have to let go of the pole. For obvious reasons, you don&amp;#39;t want to jump directly onto the ground while moving at Mach 1. Instead, you should probably wait until you&amp;#39;re somewhere near airline cruising altitude, where the air is still thin, so it&amp;#39;s not pulling at you too hard—and let go of the pole. Then, as the air carries you away and you fall toward the Earth, you can open your parachute.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;We&amp;#39;ll wait here. Next window is in the early 2040s.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/parachute.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Then, at last, you can drift safely to the ground, having traveled from the Moon to the Earth completely under your own muscle power.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;That&amp;#39;s one large, supremely complicated and unnecessary sliding-and-falling-and-tumbling step for a man, one giant but equally pointless leap for mankind.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/drift.png&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;(When you&amp;#39;re done, remember to remove the fire pole. That thing is &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; a safety hazard.)&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;img class=&#34;illustration&#34; title=&#34;In retrospect, we could have just made the magic pole lengthen and shrink to avoid hitting anyone. But you can&amp;#39;t spend your life looking backward.&#34; src=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/imgs/a/157/hazard.png&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] For one, someone at NASA would probably yell at us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[2] Ok, that&amp;#39;s a lie—there are, like, hundreds more problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[3] You may occasionally see people get excited about the &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supermoon&#34;&gt;supermoon&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;quot; a full Moon that appears slightly larger because it happens at the time of the month when the Moon is closest to Earth. But really, the full Moon always looks surprisingly large and pretty when it&amp;#39;s near the horizon, thanks to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moon_illusion&#34;&gt;Moon illusion&lt;/a&gt;. In my opinion, it&amp;#39;s worth &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/moonreminder&#34;&gt;going outside and looking at the Moon&lt;/a&gt; whenever it&amp;#39;s full, regardless of whether it&amp;#39;s super or not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[4] Of &lt;em&gt;course&lt;/em&gt; there&amp;#39;s a world record for pole climbing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[5] Of &lt;em&gt;course&lt;/em&gt; there are championship competitions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[6] As usual, anyone arguing about &amp;quot;centrifugal&amp;quot; versus &amp;quot;centripetal&amp;quot; force will &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/123/&#34;&gt;be put in a centrifuge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[7] At the distance of the Moon&amp;#39;s orbit and the speed it&amp;#39;s traveling, centrifugal force pushing away is exactly balanced by the Earth&amp;#39;s gravity—which is why the Moon orbits there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[8] This is why anything that falls into the Earth hits the atmosphere fast enough to burn up. Even if an object is moving slowly when it&amp;#39;s drifting through space, when it gets close to the Earth it gets accelerated up to at least escape velocity by that final segment of the trip down into the Earth&amp;#39;s gravity well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[9] People often ask why we don&amp;#39;t use rockets to slow down, to avoid the need for a heat shield. You can read this article for an explanation, but the bottom line is that changing your speed by 11 km/s takes either a tank of fuel the size of a building or a tiny heat shield, and the tiny heat shield is a lot easier to carry. Thanks to heat shields, slowing down is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; easier than speeding up—which requires the aforementioned giant fuel tank. (For more on this, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/58/&#34;&gt;this What If question&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Heat shields only work for slowing down; if there were a way to use the same heat shield mechanism to speed &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt;, space travel would get a lot easier. Sadly, no one&amp;#39;s figured out a practical way to build a &amp;quot;reverse heat shield&amp;quot; rocket. However, while the idea seems silly, in a sense it&amp;#39;s sort of the principle behind both &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_Orion_(nuclear_propulsion)&#34;&gt;Project Orion&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.osti.gov/biblio/21439582&#34;&gt;laser ablation propulsion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[10] Yes, I know, orbits are conic sections which in the case of the Moon is &lt;em&gt;technically&lt;/em&gt; not exactly a circle. It&amp;#39;s actually a pentagon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[11] I mean, unfortunately in this specific context. In general, the fact that the Earth spins is very fortunate for you, and for the planet&amp;#39;s overall habitability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[12] It&amp;#39;s common knowledge that Mt. Everest is the tallest mountain on Earth, measured from sea level. A somewhat more obscure piece of trivia is that the point on the Earth&amp;#39;s surface farthest from its center is the summit of Mt. Chimborazo in Ecuador, due to the fact that the planet bulges out at the equator. Even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; obscure is the question of which point on the Earth&amp;#39;s surface moves the &lt;em&gt;fastest&lt;/em&gt; as the Earth spins, which is the same as asking which point is farthest from the Earth&amp;#39;s axis. The answer isn&amp;#39;t Chimborazo &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; Everest. The fastest point turns out to be the peak of Mt. Cayambe, a volcano north of Chimborazo. And now you know.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[13] Mt. Cayambe&amp;#39;s southern slope also happens to be the highest point on Earth&amp;#39;s surface directly on the Equator. I have a lot of mountain facts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[15] For aerodynamic reasons, this gear should probably make it look like you&amp;#39;re wearing a very fast airplane.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[17] If it helps, people &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; survived &lt;a href=&#34;https://jalopnik.com/5894022/what-happens-when-you-eject-out-of-a-jet-at-800-mph&#34;&gt;supersonic ejections&lt;/a&gt; before—and even a &lt;a href=&#34;http://roadrunnersinternationale.com/weaver_sr71_bailout.html&#34;&gt;supersonic aircraft disintegration&lt;/a&gt;—so there&amp;#39;s hope.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <link href="https://what-if.xkcd.com/157/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
        <published>2018-05-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    </entry>
</feed>